2019年是阿波罗11号登月50周年
The year 2019 marks the 50th anniversary of the Apollo 11 moon landing.
咱们一起用3D动画演示的登月舱内部来庆祝吧~
Let's celebrate by using 3D animation to show the inside of the Apollo Lunar Module.
走起~
Let's check it out.
如果我们要去月球
All right, so we're gonna land on the moon.
那登月舱应该长啥样呢
What should our landing vehicle look like?
早期艺术作品中有自己的想法
Early artwork got their ideas from science fiction.
那我们开始设计原型
Then, we started building prototypes.
这个有五条腿
This one had five legs.
宇航员得看到外面 所以给驾驶舱装些窗户
Our astronauts will want to see outside, so let's make a cockpit with some windows.
而最终版本只有四条腿 窗户为了减重也更小了
The final design has only four legs, and the windows are much smaller to save weight.
大约23英尺(7米)高
It was about 23-feet tall.
作为对比 这是一个人的大小
For comparison, here's the size of a person.
登月舱在纽约Bethpage由格鲁曼公司设计并制造
The LM was designed and built in Bethpage, New York, by the Grumman Corporation.
花费了六十年代大量时间和上百位工程师的精力才完成
It took hundreds of engineers and most of the 1960s to complete.
它最初名叫“月球旅行模块” 简称LEM
It was originally called the Lunar Excursion Module, or just LEM.
最终“旅行”那个词被吃了
Eventually, the word excursion was dropped from the acronym,
但大家还是按念LEM的方法念LM
but everyone still pronounced it the same, LM.
把这家伙送到月球表面可老费劲了
It was a long process to get this machine all the way to the surface of the moon.
它由土星五号发射
It was launched aboard the Saturn V rocket
和服务舱 指令舱一起前往月球
and then went to the moon along with the Service Module and Command Module.
三个舱段加一起叫做阿波罗飞船
These three parts together are what we call the Apollo Spacecraft.
而登月舱是其中唯一登月的部分
The LM was the only part that goes down to the surface of the moon.
它是首个被设计完全用于太空真空环境中的飞船
It was the first spacecraft designed to only operate in the vacuum of space.
像指令舱之类的飞船 发射时要穿过大气层 所以考虑气动外形
So for example, the Command Module needed to be really aerodynamic for the launch through the earth's atmosphere.
但登月舱只有在进入太空后才会暴露出来
The LM wasn't exposed until it was in outer space.
太空又没有空气
Since there's no air up here,
所以可以长得随心所欲一点
the outline really doesn't matter.
这就是这个飞船长得和人类之前所有的飞船都不一样的部分原因
This is part of why you get a spacecraft that looks unlike anything we've seen before.
从著名的阿波罗11号开始 一共有六次登月
Starting with the famous Apollo 11, there were a total of six moon landings
时间跨度三年
covering a span of about three years.
阿波罗13号在太空中发生意外
Apollo 13 had an accident in space
被迫提前返回 没有登月
and was forced to come home early without landing on the moon.
再早的任务中 登月舱有几次是在地球轨道上测试的
Earlier missions tested the lunar module in earth orbit,
一次在月球轨道 且并没有登月
and then once in lunar orbit without actually landing on the moon.
之后还有几次任务的计划 但因为预算裁剪而取消
More Apollo missions were planned but were canceled due to budget cuts.
登月舱分成两个部分
The LM was split up into two parts:
上升级和下降级
the ascent stage and the descent stage.
着陆时 两个部分会一起着陆月球
For the landing, both parts went to the surface of the moon.
离开时 只有上升级会起飞离开月球表面
When it's time to leave, only the ascent stage leaves the surface,
所以阿波罗中每次月球着陆都会把下降级留在月球表面
which means that each of the Apollo moon landings left behind a descent stage.
我们放大看看
Let's zoom in for a closer look.
一圈四条腿
There were four legs attached to the side.
最初是处于收起的位置
These were originally in the retracted position
这样登月舱才能放进土星五号中发射
so that the LM would fit into the Saturn V for launch.
当登月舱准备着陆的时候才会展开
Then, once they are getting ready to land, the legs are extended.
其中三条腿有撞击检测器
Three of the legs contained a contact-sensing probe,
从而告知宇航员离月面够近 可以关闭下降发动机
which told the astronauts that they were close enough to the surface to shut off the descent engine.
另一条腿上有梯子 供宇航员上下船
This leg has the ladder which the astronauts can climb down.
这条腿的侧面有一个容器内装有美国国旗
On the left side of the ladder, there's a container which holds the American flag.
下降级的形状是八边形
The shape of the descent stage is somewhat of an octagon.
其内部结构是这样的
Here's what the structure looks like underneath.
其中有五个箱型容器
Inside there were five box-shaped compartments.
中央放有下降发动机 用于月球着陆
The center one contained the decent engine which was used for landing on the moon.
想让这台发动机工作
In order to light this engine up,
我们需要两个氧化剂罐和燃料罐
we'll need two oxidizer tanks and two fuel tanks.
它们都直接供给发动机
They both feed right into the engine.
从而给我们安全着陆月球的推力
This gives us the propulsion we'll need to safely land on the moon.
而外围的这些空间可以储存设备
These outer areas are where they stored more equipment.
名字叫四分盒
They called them quadrants.
分别是1号 2号 3号 4号位
So this was quadrant one, two, three, and four.
1号位是通用储箱
Quadrant one was for general storage.
最后三次阿波罗任务中For the last three Apollo missions,
里面装的是月球车
there was the Lunar Roving Vehicle packed inside of here.
着陆后卸货展开以供使用
Once on the surface, it was unpacked and ready for use.
这能让宇航员探索登月舱周围更远的地方
This allowed them to explore much further from the lunar module.
2号位内有一个水箱
Quadrant two contained a water tank,
水箱下面是阿波罗月球表面实验包 简称ALSEP
and then below here was the Apollo Lunar Surface Experiments Package, or ALSEP,
内有一些可以进行科学实验的设备
which basically contained several science experiments for them to perform.
3号位有另一个氦气罐 氧气罐
Quadrant three had another helium tank, oxygen tank,
在几次任务中还装有反射镜
and on a few missions it carried retro-reflectors,
反射镜是一种特殊的镜子
which is a special kind of mirror.
它们最后都被留在月球表面
They were left behind on the surface of the moon,
至今科学家们都可以用它来反射地球射来的激光
and they allow scientists even today to balance laser light from the earth to the moon and back.
4号位装有模块化设备存储组件 简称MESA
Quadrant four contained the Modularized Equipment Stowage Assembly, or MESA.
如果你曾好奇 首次登月的画面是谁拍的
And if you've ever wondered how we recorded those first few steps on the moon,
答案就是放置于此的直指登船梯的相机
there's a camera here that points right towards the ladder.
着陆腿安装于主体结构上
The landing legs were attached on the main structure.
外层覆盖的像金色锡箔纸一样东西是聚脂薄膜
The covering on the outside was made out of Mylar, which looks like gold tinfoil.
它们很轻
They used it because it was lightweight
而且可以保证内部温度不会过高或过低
and it made sure that the inside temperature didn't get too hot or too cold.
这是登船梯末端的平台
This the platform that leads to the ladder,
一圈四个是尾流挡板
and these are the plume deflectors.
它们可以保护飞船不被上升级的推进器吹坏
They protected the spacecraft from the thrusters on the ascent stage.
稍后视频中会提
We'll talk about that later in the video.
在介绍上升级之前
Before we look at the ascent stage,
后半部分正片在5:50
我要先掐口饭 感谢Audible赞助本期视频
I want to thank Audible for sponsoring today's video.
恰饭恰饭恰饭恰饭
Not everyone has time to sit down and read a physical book,
but Audible allows you to listen to audiobooks
恰饭恰饭恰饭恰饭
while you go about your day. One audiobook that helped me create this video is Neil Armstrong: A Life of Flight.
It tells the story of the first man to walk on the moon and the different life events that led him there.
恰饭恰饭恰饭恰饭
And yes, it's available to listen to on Audible.
If you're ready to sign up and help support my channel,
恰饭恰饭恰饭恰饭
visit Audible.com/JaredOwen or text jaredowen to 500 500.
It's only 14.95 per month.
恰饭恰饭恰饭恰饭
However, for the month of July only,
Amazon Prime members can start and Audible membership and get three months for only 4.95.
恰饭恰饭恰饭恰饭
That's three months for the price of one.
After that, it's only 14.95 per month.
恰饭恰饭恰饭恰饭
Visit Audible.com/JaredOwen or text jaredowen to 500 500 to get started today.
好 我们继续说上升级
Okay, let's take a look at the ascent stage now.
移除外壳后 大家能看到内部的一些机械结构
If we remove the cover, you can see some of the machinery underneath.
我们从主体结构开始
Let's start with the main structure.
它们是乘员部 中部 后部设备舱
This is the crew compartment, the midsection, and the aft equipment bay.
乘员部和中部都是正常加压的
Both the crew compartment and the midsection were normally pressurized,
意思就是宇航员可以在里面安全地脱掉宇航服
which means that they can safely take off their spacesuits.
乘员部空间不大
The crew compartment didn't have a lot of room.
前面主要是控制部分
Controls were mostly in the front,
上面有两扇窗户 可以看到外面月球表面
and then there's two windows to look outside at the surface of the moon.
指令长在左侧 登月舱驾驶员在右侧
The commander was on the left, and the LM pilot was on the right.
别忘了 还有第三个宇航员在月球轨道的指令舱里
Remember, that the third astronaut was still orbiting the moon in the CSM.
着陆后 这个舱门可供宇航员离开飞船爬下登船梯
After landing, this hatch is for the astronauts to leave the cabin and start their climb down the ladder.
在中部 你会看到更多设备
In the midsection, you'll find more equipment
这个地方里面是上升发动机
and this cover which protected the ascent engine.
当然 还有回到月球轨道后和指令舱的对接口
And of course, the tunnel to dock with the Command Module once back in lunar orbit.
后部设备舱有更多的氧气 氦气罐
The aft equipment bay has more oxygen and helium tanks
还有登月舱的其他电子设备
as well as other electronics for the LM.
这边是燃料罐 另一侧是小一点的氧化剂罐
There's a fuel tank here and a smaller oxidizer tank here.
感觉再也无法直视登月舱了。。。
所以登月舱看上去像是长了俩蛋
This is the reason that we have these bulges on the side here.
燃料罐 氧化剂罐都直接供给发动机以飞离月球表面
Both of these tanks feed right into the ascent engine which was used to blast off the surface of the moon.
外部是反作用控制系统 简称RCS
On the outside is the Reaction Control System, or RCS.
四组共16个推进器
It's an arrangement of 16 thrusters in groups of four.
它们由侧面的燃料罐 氧化剂罐供给
It was powered by fuel and oxidizer tanks on the side here.
在飞行中 这些推进器可以用来为登月舱调姿
During the flight, these thrusters could be used to maneuver the LM.
尾流挡板可以挡开RCS的废气 保护下降级
The plume deflectors helped redirect the exhaust to protect the descent stage.
外面还有几个天线 供宇航员与地球上的任务控制中心通信
On the outside were several antennas to let them communicate with Mission Control back on earth.
每个登月舱的制造都花费了大量心血
So much effort went into building each Lunar Module.
可惜的是它们只能用一次
What's sad here is that they could only be used once.
多数下降级都安详地停在月球表面
Most of the descent stages are peacefully sitting on the moon
而绝大多数的上升级都在月球轨道上受控坠毁回月球
and most of the ascent stages crashed into the moon after they were discarded in lunar orbit.
有几个登月舱从未进入太空
A few lunar modules never got the chance to fly in space.
它们现在在美国东海岸的几家博物馆中
They are now located in museums along the east coast of the United States.
我是Jared 专注于制作各种东西工作原理的3D动画
My name's Jared, and I make 3D animated videos about how things work.
点击此处了解更多阿波罗飞船的内容
Click here to learn more about the Apollo Spacecraft,
记得关注我的频道
and click here to subscribe to my channel.
感谢观看 我们下期见
Thanks for watching, and I'll see you next time.